+55 31 9 96434978 Belo Horizonte, Brazil 🔯 prezeck@gmail.com

Paulo Rezeck

Software Engineer / Ph.D. Student

Portfolio: rezeck.github.io scholar.google.com.br/rezeck linkedin.com/in/rezeck

I am a highly motivated computer scientist interested in solving real-world problems and challenges involving disruptive technologies such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, computer vision, and robotics. As an expert in robotics, I had the opportunity to develop skills at both software and hardware levels, involving embedded systems, sensor networks, and mechanical and electrical design. I participated in several R&D projects for the industry, developing prototypes of teleoperated robotic systems and algorithms for detecting and tracking objects and people. Such experiences improved my interpersonal communication, organization, and leadership skills.

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

06/2019 - 10/2022*

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 🔤

UFMG is ranked as #1 Latin America CS program: http://csrankings.org/#/index?all&southamerica

Research area: Swarm Robotics, Artificial Intelligence and Probabilistic Graph Models

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

Thesis: A Stochastic Framework for Multi-Emergent Swarm Robotics Behaviors

- Robot swarm control using probabilistic modeling using ROS middleware;
- **Development of a simulation environment** for swarms of robots using Gazebo;
- Papers published and presented at the best robotics world conferences (ICRA/IROS/RAL/AURO).

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

08/2016 - 02/2019

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) Brazil 🔤 Research area: Robot Design and Robotic Swarm

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

Master's Dissertation: HeRo: An Open Platform for Robotics Research and Education

- Low cost robot design and construction using Autodesk F360 and Eagle;
- MCU firmware implementation using C/Wiring language for embedded systems.
- Kinematic control, sensor fusion using Kalman filter, mapping, and localization;

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

08/2010 - 07/2016

Brazil 🔤

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) Research area: Robot Design and Robotic Swarm

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

Bachelor's Dissertation: Development of a Framework for Experiments with Robots Swarms.

- Practice with with embedded computer (Gumstick Overo) executing OS Yocto;
- Practice with firmware implementation and hardware protocol (I2C, SPI, UART);

MASTER OF SCIENCE/INTERNSHIP IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

02/2014 - 09/2015

Germany ==

Eberhard Karls University of Tübingen

Program: Science without Borders

Research area: Robot Control, SLAM and Robot Vision

- Experience in mobile robot control (ackerman robot) and robot vision and object identification;
- Practice with filtering and sensor fusion (LiDAR, Odometry);
- Experience in simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM);

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Tech Leader / Digital Inspection of Industrial Painting Activities based on Computer Vision

08/2020 - 07/2022

Petrobras / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 🔤

Description: Recognition of human actions during the industrial painting activity using deep learning approaches.

- Technical leader of a team specialized in robotics and machine learning;
- Experience with neural networks for real-time detection of human pose (OpenPose/AlphaPose/PoseNet);
- Experience with neural networks for real-time tracking of objects (Deep SORT);
- Experience in **container software architecture** (Docker);
- Linux process communication and algorithm optimization (C++/Python/IPC/Socket/CUDA);

ROBOTICS ENGINEER / ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE ROBOTIC RACING

02/2019 - 04/2020

XQuad Team

Brazil 💁 / USA 💻

Description: Worked with a team specialized in UAV to create an AI for racing drones that can beat a human pilot. Awarded 7th/424 place at the Artificial Intelligence Robotic Racing (AIRR) competition. ¹

- Worked with a team specialized in UAV to create an AI for racing drones that can beat a human pilot;
- Experience in Linux embedded system and algorithm optimization (C++/CMake);
- Experience with visual odometry (ORBSLAM2/ROVIO/VINS) and object detection algorithms (YOLO/OpenCV);
- Awarded 7th/424 place at the Artificial Intelligence Robotic Racing (AIRR) competition.

STUDENT RESEARCHER / ADVANCED TELEOPERATION OF EXCAVATORS IN THE MINING INDUSTRY

10/2017 - 08/2020

Vale Institute of Technology (ITV) / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 💁

Description: Develop a framework for excavator teleoperation using haptic technologies and visual immersion.

- Modeling/Construction of robotic excavator prototype using off-the-shelf parts and 3D printing;
- Robotic manipulator haptic control (C++/ROS/MOVEit);
- Construction/Control of a robotic head-like device for tele-immersion (C++/OpenCV/ROS);
- Development of a master/slave systems for teleoperation (Unity/WebRTC/ROS);

STUDENT RESEARCHER/ COOPERATIVE MAGNETIC-MAPPING USING SMALL UAVS

09/2015 - 08/2017

Vale Institute of Technology (ITV) / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 📀

Description: Control of multiple drones creating a magnetic mapping for planning the ore deposits exploration.

- Experience in piloting and control drones;
- Experience with Linux embedded systems, image creation, and kernel compiling;
- Implementation of a visual interface for real-time control of drones (Python/JavaScript/QT);
- Implementation of applications for custom data acquisition and signal processing (Android Studio/Java/C++);

 $^{^1}$ XQuad 7th place in AIRR World Championship: https://xquadufmg.com

• English (proficient) • German (limited working proficiency) • Portuguese (native speaker)

OTHER PROFESSIONAL QUALIficationS

Operating Systems	Practical experience with Linux ; integrated peripherals; conceptual understanding of sysfs, udev and dbus; controlling and automating LINUX processes using shell script; etc.
Linux Network	Intermediate skills: networking tools , routing packets, networking diagnostic procedures, and firewalls configuration under Linux environments.
Programming	Python, C, C++, Java, MATLAB. Experience with embedded devices and optimized program-ming . Experience with good programming practices, clean code, debugging, and testing;
Developer Practice	Experience with version control software (Git /SVN), agile software development (Scrum framework) and project report writing; UI design (Qt) and mobile (Android Studio);
Hardware	Practice with C/Wiring microcontroller programming, especially Arduino , ESP8266/ESP32 and PIC; hardware protocol (I2C, SPI, UART); Circuit design and Assembly ;
Robotics	Mechanical and electrical design (Autodesk Fusion/Eagle), control, motion planning, path planning and cooperative robots. Extensive knowledge of ROS/ROS2. Robot Simulation (Gazebo). Computer vision for robotics using (OpenCV), pattern recognition. Deep learning and deep reinforcement learning for robotics (TensorFlow/Open AI Gym).
Teaching Assistant	Mobile Robotics (2018) & Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (2021) both at UFMG.

SELECTED MEDIA APPEARANCES

- By Wevolver, 2022. Article: "HeRo 2.0, an ultra-low cost 3D-printed robotics platform, could open swarm robotics experimentation up to all". Language: English. Link: https://www.wevolver.com/article/hero-20-an-ultra-low-cost-3d-printed-robotics-platform-could-open-swarm-robotics-experimentation-up-to-all
- By G1/Globo newspaper, 2019. Article: "UFMG researchers participate in autonomous drone competition (Pesquisadores da UFMG participam de competição com drones sem piloto)". Language: Portuguese. Link: https://g1.globo.com/mg/minas-gerais/noticia/2019/07/04/pesquisadores-da-ufmg-participam-de-competicao-com-drones-sem-piloto.ghtml
- By O Tempo newspaper, 2019. Article: "UFMG Team is finalist at an AI competition in the USA (Equipe da UFMG é finalista em competição de inteligência artificial nos EUA)". Language: Portuguese. Link: https://www.otempo.com.br/interessa/equipe-daufmg-e-finalista-em-competicao-de-inteligencia-artificial-nos-eua-1.2201181

SCIENTIFIC PRODUCTION

Journal: 7 + 1 (accepted, and under review)

Conference: 12

Workshop/Abstracts: 4

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS:

- Rezeck, P. and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). Chemistry-Inspired Pattern Formation with Robotic Swarms. In 2022 IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters and IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (RAL/IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Correa, M. F., and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). HeRo 2.0: A Low-Cost Robot for Swarm Robotics Research (pre print). In 2022 Autonomous Robots Journal (AURO).
- Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, September). Cooperative Object Transportation using Gibbs Random Fields. In 2021 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, May). Flocking-segregative swarming behaviors using Gibbs random fields. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) (pp. 8757-8763). IEEE.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS:

- (J1) Rezeck, P. and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). Chemistry-Inspired Pattern Formation with Robotic Swarms. In 2022 IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters and IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (RAL/IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- (J2) Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Correa, M. F., and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). HeRo 2.0: A Low-Cost Robot for Swarm Robotics Research (pre print). In 2022 Autonomous Robots Journal (AURO).
- (J3) Rezende, A., Miranda, V. R., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Azpúrua, H., Santos, E. R., Gonçalves, V. M., ... & Freitas, G. M. (2021). **An integrated solution for an autonomous drone racing in indoor environments**. Intelligent Service Robotics, 14(5), 641-661.
- (J4) Pires, A. G., Rezeck, P. A., Chaves, R. A., Macharet, D. G., & Chaimowicz, L. (2021). Cooperative Localization and Mapping with Robotic Swarms. Journal of Intelligent & Robotic Systems, 102(2), 1-23.
- (J5) Santos, V. G., Pires, A. G., Alitappeh, R. J., Rezeck, P. A., Pimenta, L. C., Macharet, D. G., & Chaimowicz, L. (2020). Spatial segregative behaviors in robotic swarms using differential potentials. Swarm Intelligence, 14(4), 259-284.
- (J6) Santos, E. R., Azpurua, H., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Corrêa, M. F., Vieira, M. A., Freitas, G. M., & Macharet, D. G. (2020). **Localization using ultra wideband and IEEE 802.15. 4 radios with nonlinear bayesian filters: a comparative study**. Journal of Intelligent & Robotic Systems, 99(3), 571-587.
- (J7) Azpúrua, H., Potje, G. A., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Freitas, G. M., Uzeda Garcia, L. G., Nascimento, E. R., ... & Campos, M. F. (2019). **Cooperative digital magnetic-elevation maps by small autonomous aerial robots**. Journal of Field Robotics, 36(8), 1378-1398.
- (J8) Macharet, D. G., Perez-Imaz, H. I., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Potje, G. A., Benyosef, L. C., Wiermann, A., ... & Campos, M. F. (2016). **Autonomous aeromagnetic surveys using a fluxgate magnetometer**. Sensors, 16(12), 2169.

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS:

• (C1) Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, September). Cooperative Object Transportation using Gibbs Random Fields. In 2021 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.

- (C2) Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, May). Flocking-segregative swarming behaviors using Gibbs random fields. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) (pp. 8757-8763). IEEE.
- (C3) Carvalho, L., Rezeck, P., Lima, M. V., Pinto, L., Freitas, G., Nascimento, E. R., ... & Campos, M. F. (2020, August). On the evaluation of force feedback augmented teleoperation of excavator-like mobile manipulators. In 2020 IEEE 16th International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE) (pp. 1401-1407). IEEE.
- (C4) Chaves, R., Rezeck, P., & Chaimowicz, L. (2019, December). **SwarMap: Occupancy grid mapping with a robotic swarm**. In 2019 19th International Conference on Advanced Robotics (ICAR) (pp. 727-732). IEEE.
- (C5) de Lima, M. V., Cid, A., Cadar, F., Pinto, L., **Rezeck, P.**, Grabe, T., ... & Campos, M. F. **Realimentação de Força para Teleoperação de Escavadeiras**. In 2019 14th Simpósio Brasileiro de Automação Inteligente (SBAI).
- (C6) E. R. S. Santos, H. Azpurua, P. A. F. Rezeck, M. F. S. Corrêa, G. M. Freitas and D. G. Macharet, Global Localization of Mobile Robots Using Local Position Estimation in a Geo Tagged Wireless Node Sensor Network, 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE), 2018, pp. 39-44, doi: 10.1109/LARS/SBR/WRE.2018.00017.
- (C7) Rezeck, P., Frade, B., Soares, J., Pinto, L., Cadar, F., Azpurua, H., ... & Campos, M. F. (2018, November). Framework for haptic teleoperation of a remote robotic arm device. In 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE) (pp. 170-175). IEEE.
- (C8) Rezeck, P., Cadar, F., Soares, J., Frade, B., Pinto, L., Azpurua, H., ... & Campos, M. F. M. (2018, November). An immersion enhancing robotic head-like device for teleoperation. In 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE) (pp. 164-169). IEEE.
- (C9) Rezeck, P. A., Azpurua, H., & Chaimowicz, L. (2017, November). HeRo: An open platform for robotics research and education. In 2017 Latin American Robotics Symposium (LARS) and 2017 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) (pp. 1-6). IEEE.
- (C10) Edwards, V., Rezeck, P., Chaimowicz, L., & Hsieh, M. A. (2016, October). Segregation of heterogeneous robotics swarms via convex optimization. In Dynamic Systems and Control Conference (Vol. 50695, p. V001T03A001). American Society of Mechanical Engineers.
- (C11) Perez-Imaz, H. I., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Macharet, D. G., & Campos, M. F. (2016, August). **Multi-robot 3D coverage path planning for first responders teams**. In 2016 IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE) (pp. 1374-1379). IEEE.
- (C12) Rezeck, P. A., Vieira, M. A., Chaimowicz, L., & Campos, M. F. (2013, October). On the development of a robotic system for telepresence. In 2013 Latin American Robotics Symposium and Competition (pp. 8-13). IEEE.

ABSTRACTS, POSTERS AND WORKSHOPS:

- (W1) Paulo Rezeck, Héctor Azpúrua, Mauricio Ferrari & Luiz Chaimowics. "HeRo: An Open Robot Platform for Swarm Robotics Research". Robot Swarms in the Real World From Design to Deployment (Workshop at ICRA 2021), 2021, Xi'an China.
- (W2) Azpurua, H. **Rezeck, P.**, Torre, M., Zanetti, E. Freitas, G., Garcia, L., Nascimento, E. R., Macharet, Douglas G., Campos, M. F. M. "**Detection Of Uncrushables In Ore Piles Using Small And Autonomous Aerial Robots**". In: Mines Of The Future 2018, 2018, Aachen. Aims 2018,
- (W3) Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Chaimowicz, L. "Hero: An Open Platform For Robotics Research And Education". In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference On Intelligent Robots And Systems (IROS), 2017.
- (W4) Azpurua, H. Potje, G., Rezeck, P., Macharet, D. G., Freitas, G., Garcia, L., Campos, M. F. M. "Towards a Cooperative Method For 3D Magnetic Maps Generation Using Small And Autonomous Aerial Robots". In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference On Intelligent Robots And Systems (IROS), 2017.